{"tossups": [{"question": "One side in this battle used the Pitomnik airfield to supply bomber raids on the Red October factory and Barrikady tractor works. Erwin Konig was supposedly killed at this battle in a duel against rival sniper Vasily Zaitsev. This battle turned when Erich von Manstein failed to counter Operation Uranus, leaving Friedrich Paulus\u2019 6th Army entrapped by Georgi Zhukov\u2019s Soviet troops. For ten points, name this 1942-43 battle of the Eastern Front fought for a Russian city on the Volga River.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Stalingrad</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This justice\u2019s opinion used the Contract Clause to protect the independence of Dartmouth College, and he clarified the Interstate Commerce Clause in his opinion in<em> Gibbons v. Ogden</em>. Andrew Jackson taunted this man to enforce his ruling in<em> Worcester v. Georgia</em>. For ten points, name this fourth and longest-serving Chief Justice who, in his ruling in<em> Marbury v. Madison</em>, established the Supreme Court\u2019s power of judicial review.", "answer": "John<b> Marshall</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This material was used for the Capitoline Museum\u2019s sculpture of a she-wolf with the infant Romulus and Remus. Sculptures in this artistic medium were often made using the lost-wax method. An artist used this material for a circle of six men about to be executed during the Hundred Years War, known as<em> The</em> <em>Burghers of Calais</em>, and for a nude sculpture claimed to be cast from a living model. For ten points, name this metal used by Auguste Rodin [roh-dan] to create<em> The Thinker</em> and a sculpture of its<em> Age</em>.", "answer": "<b> bronze</b> (accept The Age of<b> Bronze</b> or the<b> Bronze</b> Age)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In 1985, this organization\u2019s headquarters-in-exile was targeted in Operation Wooden Leg, an air strike in Tunisia. This group was forced out of Jordan and into Lebanon after Black September in 1970. This group was considered a terrorist organization by the US until 1991, and it signed the Oslo Accords in 1993, thus recognizing the State of Israel. Yasser Arafat once led, for ten points, what nationalist group that sought the \u201cliberation\u201d of an Arab state from Israel?", "answer": "<b> Palestinian Liberation Organization</b> (or<b> PLO</b>) Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This author described his time serving as a war emissary during a civil war in his 2012 memoir<em> There</em> <em>was a Country</em>. In a novel by this author, Clara\u2019s societal status prevents Obi from marrying her. This author of<em> No Longer at Ease</em> advocated for the state of Biafra and created a character who commits suicide after the people of Umuofia refuse to fight against British missionaries. Okonkwo was created by, for ten points, what Nigerian author of<em> Things Fall Apart</em>?", "answer": "Chinua<b> Achebe</b> (or Albert Chinualumogu<b> Achebe</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "In this state, James Earl Chaney, Andrew Goodman, and Michael Schwerner were killed by a lynch mob in Neshoba County. This state\u2019s penitentiary at Parchman Farm held hundreds of Freedom Riders under arrest by order of Governor Ross Barnett. In 1955 in this state, J.W. Milam and Roy Bryant kidnapped and murdered 14-year-old Emmett Till. For ten points, name this state where, in 1963, Byron de la Beckwith murdered civil rights activist Medgar Evers at his home in the state capital, Jackson.", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader abolished his country\u2019s Planning Commission and replaced it with the NITI Aayog. This leader launched an economic plan promising \u201cHousing for All\u201d by the year 2022. Over the 2016 Labor Day Weekend, over 100 million workers took part in a strike against this leader\u2019s efforts towards privatization. This leader is criticized for his role in the 2002 anti-Muslim riots in the state of Gujarat. For ten points, name this leader elected in 2014 after defeating the INC, the current Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "Narendra<b> Modi</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This group pulled its support for Jimmy Walker, partly because of his frequent affairs with \u201cchorus girls.\u201d An image captioned \u201cLet Us Prey\u201d depicted this group\u2019s members as vultures. This institution was very popular among Irish immigrants, was mocked by the cartoons of reformer Thomas Nast, and was once led by the corrupt \u201cBoss\u201d Tweed. New York City was long under the control of, for ten points, what Democratic Party political machine?", "answer": "<b> Tammany</b> Hall (or Society of Saint<b> Tammany</b>; or Sons of Saint<b> Tammany</b>; or the <b>Columbian</b> Order) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This party was founded by the Tamworth Manifesto, and it provided the vast majority of seats for the first National Government. It came to power after the Winter of Discontent, and it won the \u201cCoupon\u201delection of 1918 under David Lloyd George. Under Balfour and Disraeli, this party opposed the Liberals in the 19th century, and its 20th century prime ministers included Margaret Thatcher and Winston Churchill. For ten points, name this center-right party that opposes Labour in the modern United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b> Conservative</b> and Unionist Party (accept<b> Tory</b> Party)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The death of this state\u2019s governor-elect, Eugene Talmadge, sparked the Three Governors controversy. This state is the site of Fort Benning, the infantry training site for the US Army, as well as a Lockheed Martin aircraft plant in Marietta. This home state of the Center for Disease Control was where John Pemberton invented an opium-free soft drink. For ten points, name this southern U.S. state where CNN was founded, and Coca-Cola is headquartered, in Atlanta.", "answer": "<b> Georgia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This dynasty began a system of tax farming called the<em> iqta</em> that was reformed into hereditary grants by the Buyids, one of many groups to succeed it. One ruler of this dynasty gifted a clock and an elephant to Charlemagne and founded the House of Wisdom. Harun al-Rashid was a ruler of, for ten points, which Islamic caliphate, the successors to the Umayyads, that ruled until Hulagu Khan sacked its capital, Baghdad?", "answer": "<b> Abbasid</b> Caliphate", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man died before completing the \u201cTenth Walk\u201d portion of his<em> Reveries of a Solitary Walker</em>. This author\u2019s epistolary novel about two lovers at the foot of the Alps was the best-selling novel of the 18th century. This man\u2019s two submissions to the Academy of Dijon constituted his<em> Discourse on the Arts and</em> <em>Sciences</em> and<em> Discourse on Inequality</em>, which develop his ideas of the \u201cnoble savage.\u201d For ten points, name this French Enlightenment philosopher who contrasted life under government with the ideal community of man living in nature in his<em> The Social Contract</em>.", "answer": "Jean-Jacques<b> Rousseau</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. The secret 1915 Treaty of London supported this goal via a promise regarding South Tyrol. A group of quick infantry known as the Bersaglieri fought for this goal. The Expedition of the Thousand was made in support of this goal, which was engineered by Count Cavour and Giuseppe Garibaldi. For ten points, name this 19th century nationalist process, known as the Risorgimento, which formed a modern country with its capital at Rome.", "answer": "<b> Italian unification</b> (or equivalent descriptions of<b> Italy</b> becoming a<b> unified</b> country; accept <b>Risorgimento</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One piece by this composer depicts the Paris catacombs and a planned monument to celebrate the failure of an assassination attempt on Alexander II. Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov arranged this man\u2019s music for a tone poem depicting a witches\u2019 Sabbath on St. John\u2019s Eve. The drawings of Viktor Hartmann inspired a suite by this man that ends with \u201cThe Great Gate of Kiev\u201d and includes a recurring Promenade theme. For ten points, name this Russian composer of<em> Night on Bald Mountain</em> and<em> Pictures at an Exhibition</em>.", "answer": "Modest<b> Mussorgsky</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Citizens of this country, including Arthur Rudolph, were brought to the United States in Operation Paperclip. This country\u2019s scientists developed a liquid-propellant engine for use in the first man-made object to cross the Karman line into outer space; that object was used a \u201cvengeance weapon\u201d in 1944. For ten points, name this country whose rocket scientists, including Werner Von Braun, developed the V-2 rocket but did not create a nuclear weapon before it lost World War II.", "answer": "Nazi<b> Germany</b> (or the<b> Third Reich</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In</b><em><b> Europa Universalis 4</b></em><b>, this empire may choose to lose 100 military power in exchange for a 10 percent national manpower modifier when utilizing the Devshirme system. In the</b> <em><b>Total War</b></em><b> franchise, this empire\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Nizam i-Cedit soldiers are named for its real-life</b> <b>military reforms carried out by Selim III. In</b><em><b> Civilization 5</b></em><b>, this empire\u2019s naval maintenance costs are reduced by 67 percent due to the (*)</b> \u201cBarbary Corsairs\u201d skill, and it can recruit Sipahi horseman and Janissary units. For ten points, name this empire represented in numerous video games by Suleiman the Magnificent.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A \u201csecret city\u201d in this state was home to the K-25 and Y-12 plants, which</b> <b>enriched uranium for the (+)</b> <b>Manhattan Project. The self-proclaimed State of Franklin</b> <b>was established in the eastern portion of this state, where the city of (*)</b> Oak Ridge was built in 1942 west of Knoxville. For ten points, name this state that shares the Great Smoky Mountains with its eastern neighbor, North Carolina, and has its capital at Nashville.", "answer": "<b> Tennessee</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A kingdom in this region launched the Gihae Eastern Expedition to eradicate piracy on a nearby island. The Silla kingdom ruled this location until its 935 annexation by the (+) Goryeo dynasty, which helped provide this location\u2019s name. A phonetic alphabet native to this region, hangul, was introduced by (*)</b> Sejong the Great of the Joseon Dynasty, who sought an alliance with Ming China. For ten points, name this East Asian peninsula that has been divided between two countries since a 1950s war.", "answer": "<b> Korea</b>n Peninsula", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Four men who performed this action were protected by the Supreme Court\u2019s ruling in </b><em><b>United States v. O\u2019Brien</b></em><b>, which established how the Court treated content-neutral speech.</b> <b>Students wearing black (+)</b> <b>armbands and performing this action were protected by the</b> <b>Court\u2019s ruling in</b><em><b> Tinker v. Des Moines</b></em><b>. People performing this action were described as\u201cdoves\u201d and often chanted \u201cHey, hey, (*)</b> LBJ, how many kids did you kill today?\u201d For ten points, name this political action in which U.S. citizens expressed their opposition to a conflict in Southeast Asia.", "answer": "<b> protesting</b> the<b> Vietnam</b> War (accept equivalent descriptions; prompt on partial answers; prompt on answers of \u201cburning draft cards\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Louis XII was invited by Venice to conquer this city, although he was eventually forced out after the battles of Ravenna and Novara. This city contains the only Gothic cathedral in Italy. After the death of (+) Filip Maria Visconti, this city briefly experienced the Golden Ambrosian Republic. This city led a league that opposed Emperor Frederick II and won the Battle of (*)</b> Legnano, and it was ruled in the Renaissance by Francesco, Ludovico, and other members of the Sforza family. For ten points, name this northern Italian city, the historic capital of Lombardy.", "answer": "<b> Milan</b>  (1) <b>This man\u2019s attempt to avoid conflict was documented in a telegram to \u201ccousin</b> <b>Willy.\u201d Father Gapon\u2019s insurrection took place during the reign of this ruler, who was</b> <b>persuaded to sign the (+) October manifesto after angering the populace on Bloody</b> <b>Sunday. In the mid-20th century, numerous imposters claimed to be this man\u2019s (*)</b> daughter, Anastasia, who was killed with the rest of this man\u2019s family by the Bolsheviks in 1918. For ten points, name this final Romanov Tsar of Russia. ANSWER:<b> Nicholas II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}